<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>hardware on Adam Ormsby</title>
    <link>https://www.adamormsby.com/tags/hardware/</link>
    <description>Recent content in hardware on Adam Ormsby</description>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.adamormsby.com/site-img/rssIcon.png</url>
      <link>https://www.adamormsby.com/site-img/rssIcon.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 06:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.adamormsby.com/tags/hardware/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>WilyKit: The MacBook That Became Wall Art</title>
      <link>https://www.adamormsby.com/posts/014-old-laptop-disassembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 06:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.adamormsby.com/posts/014-old-laptop-disassembly/</guid>
      <description>After 8 years of service, my 2013 MacBook Air finally died last year. I had always planned on keeping the lid somehow, so I took it apart and turned it into wall art.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Computers get old and die just like us. Parts fail. They become obsolete. You drop them a few too many times. It happens to <a href="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/j_WpEYAAmi8/maxresdefault.jpg">the best of us.</a> And while there are many ways to dispose of your computer - like <a href="https://www.epa.gov/recycle/electronics-donation-and-recycling">donation and recycling</a> - it can sometimes feel like letting go of a friend. I felt that way about WilyKit, so I turned it into wall art. 🙂</p>
<p>After 8 years of service, my 2013 MacBook Air finally died last year. Simple hard drive failure, <a href="https://www.ifixit.com/Guide/MacBook+Air+13-Inch+Mid+2013+Solid-State+Drive+Replacement/15181">totally fixable for a hundred bucks.</a> But I needed a more powerful computer to help with my work, so I just bought a new one instead.</p>
<p>I had always planned on keeping the lid somehow, no matter how many times its dinged-up edges caught onto my bags, my clothes, and even my skin when they were feeling extra bloodthirsty. It was just so full of memories! I took that laptop around the world, wrote stories with it, learned to code on it, dropped it on its corners until it wouldn&rsquo;t shut right, and stickered it full with the signposts of my youth. This was my companion, and I couldn&rsquo;t just give it away.</p>
<figure class="align-center "><a href="img/wilykit.jpg">
    <img loading="lazy" src="img/wilykit.jpg#center"
         alt="WilyKit, the worldly MacBook"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>WilyKit, the worldly MacBook Air</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Finally, after a year of busyness, I performed the surgery. <a href="https://www.ifixit.com/Guide/MacBook+Air+13-Inch+Mid+2013+Display+Assembly+Replacement/15407">Removing the upper display</a> was quite easy, but after that I was on my own. Though most of the remaining work boiled down to peeling away the layers, the screen material can get pretty nasty when it cracks! I probably should have worn long sleeves, goggles, and a mask to be extra careful with the &rsquo;exploding&rsquo; glass particles, but it was manageable. Gloves helped a lot. What would&rsquo;ve helped more is if I hadn&rsquo;t cracked the glass&hellip; but it was a fun project overall.</p>
<p>Bit by bit, I removed the bezel, many layers of screen, the hinge, and copious amounts of adhesive tape used to keep it all together&hellip; and voilà! An aluminum memory, all my own.</p>
<p>This computer had a life. And a death. Her name was WilyKit, and she can live on my wall forever.</p>
<figure class="align-center "><a href="img/display-off.jpg">
    <img loading="lazy" src="img/display-off.jpg#center"
         alt="MacBook Air disassembled"/> </a>
</figure>

<figure class="align-center "><a href="img/layered-screen-shiny.jpg">
    <img loading="lazy" src="img/layered-screen-shiny.jpg#center"
         alt="MacBook Air display with bezel removed"/> </a>
</figure>

<figure class="align-center "><a href="img/layered-screen.jpg">
    <img loading="lazy" src="img/layered-screen.jpg#center"
         alt="MacBook Air display screen layer"/> </a>
</figure>

<figure class="align-center "><a href="img/wilykit-final.jpg">
    <img loading="lazy" src="img/wilykit-final.jpg#center"
         alt="WilyKit, the MacBook Air lid turned into wall air"/> </a>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
