<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Cycling on Adam Ormsby</title>
    <link>https://www.adamormsby.com/tags/cycling/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cycling on Adam Ormsby</description>
    <image>
      <title>Adam Ormsby</title>
      <url>https://www.adamormsby.com/site-img/rssIcon.png</url>
      <link>https://www.adamormsby.com/site-img/rssIcon.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.147.9</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.adamormsby.com/tags/cycling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Road to Viñales - A Tale of Cycling in Cuba - Part 3</title>
      <link>https://www.adamormsby.com/posts/000/adam-roams-cycling-vinales/part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.adamormsby.com/posts/000/adam-roams-cycling-vinales/part-3/</guid>
      <description>At first I didn’t realize it was a mountain. All I knew was that I had ridden out past the edge of a small town to a place where the road suddenly changed. It curved back and forth, meandering upward through forested hills, becoming steeper and more narrow as I rode on. Time passed, and the shoulders of the road disappeared.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Road to Viñales - A Tale of Cycling in Cuba - Part 2</title>
      <link>https://www.adamormsby.com/posts/000/adam-roams-cycling-vinales/part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.adamormsby.com/posts/000/adam-roams-cycling-vinales/part-2/</guid>
      <description>I stopped at around 7 PM that first night to search for a place to stay. With the hammock and sleeping bag stuffed deep inside my pack I had dreamed of camping in the countryside and experiencing a night under the stars in Cuba. Sadly, that dream was crushed by the sheer amount of private farmland that bordered the highway for the entire ride, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to get in trouble for camping on private land or government property.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Road to Viñales - A Tale of Cycling in Cuba - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://www.adamormsby.com/posts/000/adam-roams-cycling-vinales/part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.adamormsby.com/posts/000/adam-roams-cycling-vinales/part-1/</guid>
      <description>As I lay on the side of the road, the afternoon sun bearing down on me and threatening to steal away my consciousness, I could hear the throaty rumble of a motor headed my way. I barely registered the rusty blue taxi that passed little more than arm’s length in front of me, leaving a cloud of lead-laden exhaust in its wake. Exhaustion spread through me like a virus, and I sat still in the silence.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
